{"tossups": [{"question": "This person sued author William Manchester in order to get family information removed from a 1967 book. Late in life, this person worked as a book editor for Doubleday and edited such books as The Cartoon History of the Universe. In film footage, this person is shown being pushed back into a seat by Clint Hill. In a television special broadcast on Valentine's Day on multiple networks, this person takes a CBS reporter through her home, which had recently undergone a million dollar restoration. In an interview with Life, she compared recent years of her life to the musical Camelot. In a photograph, this woman is shown wearing a bloodstained pink suit as she stands next to Lyndon Johnson. For 10 points, name this First Lady, the wife of a president assassinated in 1963.", "answer": "Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Kennedy [or Jackie Kennedy; or Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Bouvier; or Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Onassis; prompt on Kennedy]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Jacqueline \"Jackie\" <b><u>Kennedy</u></b> [or <b><u>Jackie Kennedy</u></b>; or <b><u>Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Bouvier</u></b>; or <b><u>Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Onassis</u></b>; prompt on <u>Kennedy</u>]", "acceptable": ["Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Kennedy", "Jackie Kennedy", "Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Bouvier", "Jacqueline \"Jackie\" Onassis"], "promptable": ["Kennedy"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Tolman electronic parameter for a ligand is calculated from changes it causes in this molecule's IR vibration at 2143 inverse centimeters. The Gattermann\u00c2\u2013Koch reaction allows formylation of benzene with the use of a Lewis acid, hydrochloric acid, and this compound. Cytochrome p450s are named for the fact that they exhibit an absorbance maximum at 450 nanometers when complexed to this compound. This molecule, which is found with cyanide at the top of the spectrochemical series, is used with hydrogen gas to generate liquid hydrocarbons in the Fischer\u00c2\u2013Tropsch process. The Mond process purifies nickel by reacting it with this molecule, and it plus water vapor gives carbon dioxide and hydrogen gas in the water-gas shift reaction. For 10 points, name this molecule is toxic in the bloodstream because it binds hemoglobin to generate carboxyhemoglobin.", "answer": "carbon monoxide [or CO until it is read] ", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>carbon monoxide</u></b> [or <b><u>CO until it is read</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["carbon monoxide", "CO until it is read"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "An endangered dialect of this language is the only dialect to possess an open back rounded vowel, which is called arae-a (AH-ray AH). In this language, obstruents are phonemically differentiated between plain, aspirated, and tense varieties. This is the most widely-spoken language to possess an aspirated /s/ (ess). This language uses a featural writing system that combines consonants and vowels into individual \"blocks\" for each syllable. It uses a namesake Revised Romanization system and, like Japanese, it uses a particle, neun (nun), to mark the topic. Despite being an isolate, this language borrows around 60 percent of its vocabulary from Chinese, but uses an alphabet created in 1443 by Sejong the Great. For 10 points, name this language written in Hangul.", "answer": "Korean language [or Hanguk-eo; or Hanguk-mal; do not accept \"Hangul\"]", "category": "Social Science", "subcategory": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Korean language</u></b> [or <b><u>Hanguk-eo</u></b>; or <b><u>Hanguk-mal</u></b>; do not accept \"Hangul\"]", "acceptable": ["Korean language", "Hanguk-eo", "Hanguk-mal"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A soldier modeled after Donatello's St. George leans on his shield in a fresco painted in this city's now-destroyed Ovetari Chapel, which was bombed during World War II. St. James Led to His Execution is the culmination of Mantegna's early career, which was spent in this city. Clubs and torches dominate the top half of a painting in this city focused on two men embracing. Another painting in this city is set near a leafless tree above a diagonal rocky hill, over which ten angels fly wildly. The Lamentation, Kiss of Judas, and The Last Judgment and are part of a series in this city commissioned by the banker Enrico Scrovegni. For 10 points, name this northern Italian city home to the Giotto-decorated Arena Chapel.", "answer": "Padua", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Padua</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Padua"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The debut performance of this play was a benefit for the 25th anniversary of a comedy star's debut, which explained why a crowd expecting humor legendarily booed and talked over the production. Early in this play, a female character spots two red points she claims are the lurid eyes of Satan, prompting another woman to obnoxiously say she smells sulfur. Near the end of this play, a woman halts a metaphor by abruptly saying \"I am an actress\" and recites a monologue she earlier performed in an outdoor play in Act 1. This play's reputation was improved by a December 1898 performance directed by Konstantin Stanislavsky which inspired the emblem of the Moscow Art Theater. In this play, Nina loves the writer Trigorin. For 10 points, name this Anton Chekhov play in which Konstantin shoots both himself and the title bird.", "answer": "The Seagull", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Seagull</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Seagull"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One of the first original theological texts from this country analyzes how the cross is a synthesis of love and wrath called the \"pain of God\". The patron saint of Mexico City died in this country, whose \"non-church\" movement does not believe in liturgy or clergy. A missionary here named James Curtis Hepburn wrote an influential dictionary of English and this country's language. Its \"twenty-six\" martyrs were forced to walk 600 miles to be crucified in 1597 and include Paul Miki. Suspected believers here were ordered to step on pictures of Jesus or Mary to prove they were not Christian. In January 1548, the missionary Francis Xavier began spreading Catholicism in this country. For 10 points, what country's hidden \"Christians\" were known as kakure kirishitan?", "answer": "Japan [or Nippon]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Japan</u></b> [or <b><u>Nippon</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Japan", "Nippon"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "After criticizing this man, comedian Eddie Cantor was put out of work for two years. This man was instructed to cease his activities by Eugenio Pacelli during the latter's tour of America. Both Frank Murphy and Joseph Kennedy were sent to ensure this man would not run for president. Attorney General Francis Biddle rescinded the mailing privileges of this man's magazine in April 1942. He joined Dr. Francis Townsend and Gerald L. K. Smith in backing William Lemke's presidential run with the Union Party. This head of the National Union for Social Justice was based at Royal Oak, Michigan, at the National Shrine of the Little Flower church. For 10 points, what Catholic priest promoted left-wing ideology and antisemitism over the radio in the 1930s?", "answer": "Father Charles Edward Coughlin ", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Father Charles Edward Coughlin</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Father Charles Edward Coughlin"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In the \"Alla Hornpipe\" movement from Water Music, two of these instruments play a solo right after the opening tutti. Vivaldi wrote a C major double concerto for this instrument. An E major concerto for it is often transposed to E-flat major to make it easier to play. This instrument has a prominent solo part in the second Brandenburg Concerto. An E-flat major concerto for its short-lived keyed variety was written by Joseph Haydn. Two popular wedding pieces composed by Jeremiah Clarke are this instrument's namesake \"tune\" and namesake \"voluntary\". The mellow sound of the similarly-shaped cornet contrasts with the buzzing texture of this instrument used to play fanfares. For 10 points, name this highest-pitched brass instrument.", "answer": "trumpet", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>trumpet</u></b>", "acceptable": ["trumpet"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One character in this novel believes only courage and shrewdness are required to be successful, the former of which he has and the latter of which he can acquire. Another character in this novel nails himself in his attic and starves to death after his store is looted. After putting down a slave rebellion in Haiti, a man in this novel returns to the United States and gets a hundred miles of land from a drunken Indian. Shreve narrates parts of this novel set in a cold Harvard bedroom. Henry murders Charles Bon to prevent him from marrying Judith in this novel narrated by Rosa Coldfield and Quentin Compson. For 10 points, name this biblically titled novel about the life of Thomas Sutpen, a work of William Faulkner.", "answer": "Absalom, Absalom! ", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Absalom, Absalom!</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Absalom, Absalom!"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Production of this molecule is increased by London and Arctic mutations and is diminished by an allele found in some Icelanders. Site-specific levels of this molecule were integral to the now- discounted \"peripheral sink\" hypothesis. This molecule can be imaged with PET using Pittsburgh compound B. Its degradation is lowered in people with the ApoE epsilon 4 allele. A protein triplicated in Down syndrome is processed into C99 before being refined into this molecule. This 40- to 42-residue peptide is generated by PSEN1 in the gamma secretase complex following BACE-1 cleavage of the precursor protein APP. Cortical deposition of it accelerates tau propagation and formation of neurofibrillary tangles. For 10 points, name this peptide that comprises the insoluble plaques seen in Alzheimer's disease.", "answer": "amyloid beta [or beta-amyloid; prompt on plaque; prompt on amyloid precursor protein or APP until \"peripheral\" is read]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>amyloid beta</u></b> [or <b><u>beta-amyloid</u></b>; prompt on <u>plaque</u>; prompt on <u>amyloid precursor protein</u> or <u>APP until \"peripheral\" is read</u>]", "acceptable": ["amyloid beta", "beta-amyloid"], "promptable": ["plaque", "amyloid precursor protein", "APP until \"peripheral\" is read"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Before using this thing, a woman repeats the cry \"Wise!\" despite her husband's insistence it is \"foolish\". After the final time it is used, a man opens a door to reveal \"a quiet and deserted road\". This thing was created by \"a very holy man... to show that fate ruled people's lives\" and its first owner ended up killing himself. It is thrown onto the fire by Sergeant-Major Morris, who obtained it while abroad in India. This item is last being used to prevent the presumably horribly mutilated Herbert from entering his parents' home. This thing is responsible for Mr. and Mrs. White earning 200 pounds but only through the workplace death of their son. For 10 points, name this title object of a W. W. Jacobs story which grants three wishes, albeit in horrible ways.", "answer": "the monkey's paw [prompt on paw; do not accept \"monkey\"]", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>the monkey's paw</u></b> [prompt on <u>paw</u>; do not accept \"monkey\"]", "acceptable": ["the monkey's paw"], "promptable": ["paw"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "After obtaining an object created by this god, Setna dreams that he sacrifices his wife and children to cats out of love for a woman who turns out to be a corpse. Nefrekeptah is cursed after reading a book of spells written by this deity. A syncretic combination of Hermes and this god is the purported author of the Corpus Hermeticum. This god and Shu convince Tefnut to return from the Nubian Desert. After Horus was stung by a scorpion, this god healed him. This god, whose feminine counterpart was Seshat, was worshipped at Hermopolis. He defeated the moon god Khonsu in a gambling contest to win five extra days for Nut. For 10 points, name this inventor of writing, an Egyptian god of wisdom and magic depicted as a baboon or an ibis.", "answer": "Thoth [or Djehuty]", "category": "Mythology", "subcategory": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Thoth</u></b> [or <b><u>Djehuty</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Thoth", "Djehuty"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A prince and princess from this region married a princess and a prince from Bavaria in a double wedding held at Cambrai. In a phase of the Hook and Cod wars, the conservative Hooks supported Jacqueline of Bavaria while the Cods supported a ruler of this region. That man established the Order of the Golden Fleece here after his marriage to Isabella of Portugal. A leader of this region put down several rebellions by the city of Lie\u0300ge and forged an alliance with England by marrying Margaret of York. A duke of this region supported the League of the Public Weal against his longtime rival Louis XI before his death at the Battle of Nancy. For 10 points, name this region in France ruled by John the Fearless, Philip the Good, and Charles the Bold.", "answer": "Burgundy", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Burgundy</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Burgundy"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Dick Pound described this crisis as \"manufactured\" and said it did not apply to many people. Attempts to resolve this crisis have led to fears that Oxitec's actions might damage the ecosystem. The ill-advised joke \"I'm fast\u00c2\u2014they can't catch me\" was made about it during a television interview. In discussing potential solutions to this crisis, Pope Francis condemned \"taking one life to save another.\" It was responsible for a May 2016 series of games between the Marlins and Pirates being relocated to Miami, and has been linked by conspiracy theorists to vaccines and genetically modified animals. Countries such as Colombia have advised women not to get pregnant because of this crisis. For 10 points, what epidemic poses a potential threat for the 2016 Summer Olympics in Brazil?", "answer": "Zika virus epidemic [or ZIKV epidemic]", "category": "Current Events", "subcategory": "Current Events", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Zika virus epidemic</u></b> [or <b><u>ZIKV epidemic</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Zika virus epidemic", "ZIKV epidemic"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a technique named for its use of this process, liquid helium is used to keep a sample at a constant temperature and then removed right before this process occurs isentropically, reducing the internal energy and temperature of the sample. The portion of a B\u00c2\u2013H graph, or hysteresis loop, in the second quadrant is sometimes known as this phenomenon's curve. The last stages of cooling a sample to the microkelvin or picokelvin range involves the \"nuclear\" and \"adiabatic\" types of this process. A measure of the ability to resist this process is coercivity. For 10 points, name this process that one might perform by slowly removing a ferromagnet from a coil of wire that has alternating current flowing through it, or by heating a ferromagnet above the Curie temperature.", "answer": "demagnetization [or adiabatic demagnetization; or nuclear demagnetization]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>demagnetization</u></b> [or <b><u>adiabatic demagnetization</u></b>; or <b><u>nuclear demagnetization</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["demagnetization", "adiabatic demagnetization", "nuclear demagnetization"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This architect designed a vaulted ceiling made up of reinforced concrete shells buttressed by double columns for a naturally-lit church with an all-white interior. Inspired by patterns in nature, this architect devised the notion that buildings are the sum total of their constitutive repeating elements, a framework he called \"additive architecture\". This architect combined a flat-roofed mosque with a public square topped with an inclined roof rising toward the Persian Gulf in a collaborative design with his son Jan (yann) for the Kuwait National Assembly Building. In 1966, he resigned from a project for which he designed a two-hall complex topped by sail-shaped shells. For 10 points, name this Danish-born architect of the Sydney Opera House.", "answer": "J\u00c3\u00b8rn Utzon (yurn OOT-sun) [or J\u00c3\u00b8rn Oberg Utzon]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "J\u00c3\u00b8rn <b><u>Utzon</u></b>", "acceptable": ["J\u00c3\u00b8rn Utzon"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "yurn OOT-sun"}, {"question": "In a play set in this state, a man is berated for missing the funeral of the family patriarch, who is later revealed to be his actual father. A play set here ends with a maid repeating the line \"This is the way the world ends\", and details the effects of Beverly Weston's suicide on his drug-addicted wife, Violet. Muley Graves angrily refuses to leave his farm in this state. This state is the setting of a 2007 play by Tracy Letts and the location of McAlester prison in a novel that opens with its protagonist being paroled from his homicide charge. The drama August: Osage County is set here, and it is the starting point of a journey to California that is undertaken by Jim Casy. For 10 points, name this home state of the Joad family in John Steinbeck's The Grapes of Wrath.", "answer": "Oklahoma", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Oklahoma</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Oklahoma"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "To establish a link between Nevanlinna theory and the theory of this kind of approximation, Kobayashi proposed a modified form of the truncated counting function. The subspace theorem concerns curves defined by this kind of function, such as the S-unit function. In general, this kind of approximation is concerned with using rational numbers to approximate the reals. By resolving Hilbert's tenth problem, Yuri Matiyasevich showed that there cannot be a universal algorithm for solving these problems. Catalan's Conjecture concerned one of these equations, another example of which is Pell's equation. The ancient Greek author of the Arithmetica gave his name to, for 10 points, what equations in which only integer solutions are sought?", "answer": "Diophantine equations", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Diophantine equations</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Diophantine equations"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A 1925 law ended the practice of appointing \"mahants\", managers of these buildings who did not belong to the religion that makes use of these facilities. Within these buildings, the practice of \"katha\" takes place as part of a ceremony that always ends with a divine reply known as \"hukam\". The five takhts are major examples of this type of building. Each of these facilities, whose largest example is the Harmandir Sahib, contains a communal kitchen called a \"langar\" and a canopy-covered cot which holds a copy of the Adi Granth. For 10 points, name these centers, such as the Golden Temple of Amritsar, which are the worship places for the followers of a religion founded by Guru Nanak.", "answer": "gurdwaras [or Sikh temples]", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>gurdwaras</u></b> [or <b><u>Sikh temples</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["gurdwaras", "Sikh temples"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Anticipating the end of this battle, thousands of NDH members fled north but were repatriated to Bleiburg shortly afterward. This battle was the culmination of a campaign that included battles at Seelow Heights and Halbe. The winners of this battle were pressured to take a government building by May Day for a photo opportunity. The losing side of this battle destroyed much of their official documents as part of Operation Clausewitz. A picture taken by Yevgeny Khaldei shows a soldier raising a flag atop an enemy's parliament building in the aftermath of this battle. Karl Do\u0308nitz (DER-nitz) became president during this battle after a higher-up committed suicide. For 10 points, name this battle that brought an end to the European theater of World War II by forcing Germany to surrender.", "answer": "Battle of Berlin", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Berlin</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Berlin"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In this text, the narrator says he is captivated by stage plays which provide \"fuel\" for his own fire of miseries. At one point in it, two men who have jobs sometimes translated as \"secret service agents\" resign to live in a cottage. In part nine of this text, the author describes being overjoyed to end his professorship of teaching rhetoric, after which he has an ecstatic experience in Ostia. The author of this text recalls robbing a pear tree with his friends and is ashamed to have thrown most of the food to the hogs. While in a garden, its narrator hears a voice saying \"take up and read\", prompting him to read Romans 13. The author of this text recalls the death of his mother, Monica, and describes how he converted from Manichaeism to Christianity. For 10 points, name this autobiographical text by Saint Augustine.", "answer": "The Confessions of Saint Augustine [or Confessions in Thirteen Books]", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Confessions of Saint Augustine</u></b> [or <b><u>Confessions in Thirteen Books</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["The Confessions of Saint Augustine", "Confessions in Thirteen Books"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}